从传说盘古开了天
According to legend, Pangu opened the sky,
然后女娲造了神仙
then Nüwa created immortals (the first batch of humans were superior to the common people).
而炎黄战在了黄河边
Where the Flame Emperor and Yellow Emperor fought each other by the Yellow River,
才逐渐有了人烟
human civilization gradually rose.
先有仓颉造字
After Cangjie created writing,
写下了后羿射日
the story of Hou Yi shooting the sun was written down,
再有精卫展翅
then so was the story of Jingwei spreading her wings.
说的是古人有志
Such stories reveal the ancient people's ambitions.
那大禹治水在何处
Where did Yu the Great control the floods?
而三过家门不入
And why did he refuse to enter his home three times?
因为共工的怒
It was because of Gonggong's anger.
断了擎天的柱
Gonggong broke the pillars that held up the sky.
那颗通天的树
The tree that reached the heavens
倒下成了条路
fell down and became a path.
我们一步一步
We remember each step
在口中记录
as we recite the stories.
当神话谢幕
Where the myth ends,
真正的历史才开始
only then does the real history begin.
拉开帷幕
Raise the curtains!
自尧舜时到夏商
From the time of Emperors Yao and Shun to the Xia and Shang dynasties,
从取火又到麻桑
from making fire to growing hemp and mulberry (for clothing),
那年的四海八荒
the world of ancient times was vast with four seas and eight wildernesses.
到今日剩了残光
Today, only a remnant of its light remains.
当最后一位人皇
When the last human emperor (King Zhou of Shang; future emperors became heavenly)
自鹿台誓死不降
swore to die in a fire rather than surrender at the Deer Terrace Pavilion,
以尸骨铸的高墙
the high walls built with human bones
不过是笔下两行
were reduced to nothing but two lines of text.
姜太公愿者上勾
Jiang Taigong waited auspiciously until the fish took the bait.
便定了国号为周
Thus, the name of the country was set as Zhou (dynasty).
此八百年来似无忧
For 800 years, it seemed worry-free,
却分了百个春秋
but it divided into a hundred springs and autumns.
只为了佳人一回眸
For only a glance from a beautiful woman,
以烽火戏了诸侯
feudal lords played with signal fires.
若问我要个理由
If you ask me for a reason,
我想那必是温柔
I think it must have been her gentle romance.
春秋战国五百年
The 500 years of the Spring and Autumn period and the Warring States,
这五百年的战火连
these were 500 years of continuous wars.
昔日诸子百家言
The words of the hundred schools of thought in the past
今日已成了圣贤
have now become the words of today's sages.
看老子紫气东来
Look at Laozi's purple cloud from the east
对孔子以礼相怀
and Confucius' respect for one another.
那百家经世之才
The talents of the hundred schools of thought
不尽被黄土而埋
were not all buried in the yellow dirt.
卧薪尝胆越王剑
King Goujian of Yue sleeping on sticks and tasting bile (hardship for ambition).
南门立木金不欠
The wooden post at the southern gate doesn't owe any gold (honesty and trustworthiness).
完璧归赵回金殿
Returning the Imperial Jade Seal to Zhao and entering the Golden Palace (honesty and integrity).
那一曲离骚再难见
Such a poem like "Li Sao" will rarely be seen again (exceptional beauty and sorrow).
车同轨
Vehicles follow the same road system,
书同文
and books use the same writing system.
万里长城尚有痕
The Great Wall, stretching thousands of miles, still bears its scars.
那古往今来第一人
For the greatest person throughout history,
可惜了未被封了神
it's a pity that he wasn't deified.
那千古一帝
The first emperor's eternal legacy
已自二世难续
could not last after the second generation.
问那长生何意啊
He sought the essence of immortality
用了举国之力
using the strength of the entire country.
可王侯将相宁有种
Are kings and nobles given their high status by birth (everyone born equal slogan for Chen Sheng Wu Guang uprising)?
到今日仍有人不懂
Even today, some people still don't understand.
那刘邦不及霸王勇
Although Liu Bang lacked the bravery of Xiang Yu,
可未见与人高一等
he hasn't faced anyone superior.
兄弟仇若隔了夜
If brotherly enmity is allowed to linger overnight,
便成了楚河汉界
it will lead to a border along the river dividing Chu and Han (states).
乌江畔的英雄血
As the hero's blood (Xiang Yu's) on the bank
随江水念了声妾
flowed into the Wu River, so did his concubine's tears.
他稳坐在了咸阳
And yet, the victor (Liu Bang) sat securely in Xianyang.
封了八个异姓的王
He appointed eight kings of different surnames.
可宫门外的高墙
Despite the high walls around the palace,
那刀剑却已难藏
it was already hard to hide from the knives and swords.
又是谁尊了儒术
Who was the one who respected Confucianism
将丝绸运至何处
and brought silk to distant lands (Emperor Wu of Han)?
冠军侯单枪而入
The Marquess of Champion (Huo Qubing) entered alone (talent and bravery).
自司马手中写录
Sima's hands wrote down historical records (Records of the Grand Historian).
我大汉至了结尾
As our great Han dynasty comes to an end,
这满朝窃国的匪
all the thieves in the imperial court and bandits of the country
皆怕那世人的嘴
were afraid of the people's mouths,
所以皇帝成了傀儡
so the emperor became a puppet.
到了天下三分
Thus, the empire divided into three parts.
那烈酒定是余温
The strong liquor certainly had a lingering aftertaste.
可怜这三人的根
Pity the roots of these three men.
后被司马定了乾坤
Later, Sima determined the fate of the empire.
八王之乱
During the War of the Eight Princes,
自南北分了一半
north and south divided in half.
书中的易子而换
In the historical records, people exchanged and ate children (cannibalism during famine).
更像是一声长叹
This period seems more like a long sigh.
杨广自运河而下
Yang Guang (Emperor of Sui) went down the Grand Canal
以科举传了佳话
and spread good news about the imperial examination system,
可劳民伤财遭的骂
but he was criticized more for wasting people's lives and money,
比功绩来的还大
than praised for his achievements.
那玄武门外的墙
The wall outside the Xuanwu Gate
曾也有刀剑相藏
once hid knives and swords within,
可若是没那血两行
but if there was no blood from those two (assassination of two brothers),
哪来的盛世大唐
there would be no golden age of the Tang dynasty.
千古的一位女皇
The first empress (Wu Zetian) for a thousand years,
谁说的不如儿郎
who says she is inferior to men?
无字碑无字一行
No words on her monument (wordless stone stele), no words in the historical records,
问功与过又何妨
why not question her accomplishments and shortcomings?
安史乱后无英豪
After the An Lushan Rebellion, there were no heroes,
不过是生死命一条
just a matter of life and death.
那三岁孩童戏歌谣
A three-year-old child plays and sings.
再无人比那黄巢
No one can surpass Huang Chao.
待到来年九月八
Wait until next year on Double Ninth Day;
我花开后百花杀
my flowers will bloom after various other flowers die.
冲天香阵透长安
Their fragrance will fill the sky over Chang'an,
满城尽带黄金甲
and all throughout the city, golden armor will shine.
自黄袍加在身前
After the yellow imperial robe was put on (by Emperor Taizu of Song),
以杯酒释了兵权
he consolidated military power by toasting with a cup of wine (persuading military officials).
可多年后再想当年
Many years later, when we think back to those days,
这也才是忠义两全
this was true loyalty and righteousness combined.
那靖康之祸
The Jingkang incident
到今日仍被人唾
is still being spit upon today.
那尽忠报国之诺
Serving the country with the utmost loyalty and devotion
在当年竟是为过
was considered a mistake in those days.
将军若是不还朝
If the general (Yue Fei) did not return to the imperial court,
有谁可动你分毫
who dared to lay a finger on him?
那莫须有的罪一条
Being falsely accused of a crime (by Qin Hui)
还真是罪不可饶
was truly an unforgivable sin.
自大汗铁蹄之下
Under the iron hooves of the great Khan,
也败了英雄白发
even heroes with white hair were defeated.
这普天下的佳话
This was a great story known throughout the world,
唯有那万国皆怕
the only story that all the nations feared.
是和尚还是乞丐
From being a monk and a beggar (Hongwu Emperor of Ming),
换来的山河不败
he became a ruler of invincible mountains and rivers.
那英雄便有的无奈
The heroes will have no better option than
是手中刀斧的快
the speed of the knife and ax in their hands.
可惜了土木之变
It's a pity that the Tumu Crisis happened,
让盛世再难重现
which made it difficult for a golden age to reappear.
用粉身碎骨换一遍
Sacrificing his life (Yu Qian's) for another chance (body's flesh ground into dust and bones smashed into pieces),
六月的飞雪一片
the snow in June covered his remains (abnormal false accusations leading to execution, The Injustice to Dou E).
那一日剩了一人
On the day when only one person remained,
脚下已再无群臣
with no ministers left under his feet,
便遵了祖上训的文
he followed the teachings of his ancestors (Huang-Ming Zuxun).
那天子死在国门
The emperor (Chongzhen Emperor of Ming) died at the country's gate (Meishan, a hill behind the Forbidden City).
当四方兵马来袭
When the soldiers attacked from all sides,
便走的坚定不移
only the resolute remained steadfast and firm.
这天下似个棋局
This world is like a game of chess,
唯是那当局者迷
except the players themselves are confused (while spectators can see things clearly).
冲冠一怒为红颜
Angry and impulsive, he (Wu Sangui) betrayed the Ming dynasty for a beautiful woman (Chen Yuanyuan),
也不过是个传言
but it was just a rumor that spread.
名利要在了身前
Fame and fortune are fleeting,
那骂名还了百年
but infamy lasts for a hundred years.
清兵入关平三藩
The Qing army entered and crushed the Three Feudatories
以水军收了台湾
and captured Taiwan with its navy.
也算是几座高山
These were considered great accomplishments,
错在了百年闭关
but the Qing was wrong to close its doors for a hundred years.
在闭关锁国那一日
On the day of isolation and closure,
便定了清风不识字
the cool breeze (Qing dynasty) was illiterate (so why ruffle the pages when it cannot read, poem by Xu Jun).
后来人的鸿鹄志
The high ambitions of future generations
更像是我中华的翅
are soaring higher with our Chinese wings.
从盘古到这清末
From Pangu to the end of the Qing dynasty,
又怎能就此别过
how could we stop there?
这五千年的颜色
The colors of these 5,000 years
仍在为了你我而烁
continue to shine for you and me.
我华夏儿女的乡
My ancestral home of the Chinese people
自古是礼仪之邦
has always been a land of rituals and ceremonies since ancient times,
而这个古老的东方
and this ancient East
立在了世界中央
stood in the center of the world.
今日的阳光普照
Today's sunlight shines everywhere,
是前人给的依靠
thanks to the efforts of our ancient ancestors.
此生第一个骄傲
The first pride in this life
是生来有的荣耀
is the glory we were born with.
这中华上下五千年
Up and down these 5,000 years of Chinese history,
有多少话还未言
there are many stories still untold.
还会有沧海桑田
The blue sea will continue turning into mulberry fields (drastic changes are the ups and downs of life).
由你我来续前缘
It is up to us to continue this frontier.
我等炎黄子孙
As the descendants of the Flame Emperor and Yellow Emperor,
早已骨血难分
our blood and bones have already become inseparable long ago.
若还热血尚温
If our passion still burns brightly,
看我一笔乾坤
watch us move heaven and earth with one mighty stroke of a pen.